Guide to the Bernard F. Burgunder Collection of George Bernard Shaw, [ca. 1810]-1990.
Bernard F. Burgunder Collection of George Bernard Shaw, [ca. 1810]-1990.
- Series V. Manuscripts and Correspondence to and by others
  - Musters, Judy to Ann Carr Jackson
    - Musters, Judy: Typed Letters Signed: to Ann Carr Jackson, Jul.-Aug., 1968; 15 leaves + 2 leaves (Box 115, Folder 38)
      16 Grimston Gardens, Folkestone, Kent; 14 letters & 1 postcard from Musters to Jackson plus one postcard to Jackson from her daughter, Judy; and 1 poem [Judy Musters was Shaw's first cousin. Mrs. Jackson's other correspondence is under her maiden name: Carr. She has been Shaw's second secretary.]
    - Musters, Judy: Typed Letters Signed: to Ann Carr Jackson, Sept.-Oct., 1968; 14 leaves + 3 clippings (Box 115, Folder 39)
      16 Grimston Gardens, Folkestone, Kent; 13 letters & 1 postcard & 3 clippings from Musters to Jackson [Judy Musters was Shaw's first cousin. Mrs. Jackson's other correspondence is under her maiden name: Carr. She has been Shaw's second secretary.]
    - Musters, Judy: Typed Letters Signed: to Ann Carr Jackson, Nov.-Dec., 1968; 11 leaves (Box 115, Folder 40)
    - Musters, Judy: Autographed & Typed Letters Signed: to Ann Carr Jackson, 1970-1971; 22 leaves (Box 115, Folder 41)
      16 Grimston Gardens, Folkestone, Kent; 14 letters & 1 postcard from Musters to Jackson [Judy Musters was Shaw's first cousin. Mrs. Jackson's other correspondence is under her maiden name: Carr. She has been Shaw's second secretary.]
    - Musters, Judy: Typed Letters Signed: to Ann Carr Jackson, [n.d.]; 5 leaves + 1 clipping + 1 photo (Box 115, Folder 42)
      16 Grimston Gardens, Folkestone, Kent; 4 letters from Musters to Jackson, with 1 clipping and one photo of Musters [Judy Musters was Shaw's first cousin. Mrs. Jackson's other correspondence is under her maiden name: Carr. She has been Shaw's second secretary.]
  - Patterson, Jane
    - Patterson, Jane: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, 1886-1888; copy; 527 leaves + 1 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      Photocopies of the originals in the British Library; the leaves have been numbered in pencil: leaves 1-275 are from manuscript ADD. 50544; leaves 276-527 are from manuscript ADD. 50545; with identifying note added on separate leaf by Bernard F. Burgunder, dated Jan. 27, 1982
  - Pat - Shav
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Manuscript: Description of 4 caricatures by Max Beerbohm which belonged to Shaw, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Later reprinted in her book; See: Patch, Blanche, Thirty Years With G.B.S.; pp. 29-30
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Manuscript: The Diaries... [Shaw's diaries, kept from January 1885 to December 1891], n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Contains the allegation that St. John Ervine was using transcriptions of the diaries, originally made by Miss Patch, without the proper permission
    - Patch, Blanche: Miscellaneous Writings and Opinions of George Bernard Shaw, extracted [typed and written] by his secretary, Blanche Patch, various dates; 33 leaves (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter Signed: to Gerald Christy, Apr. 7, 1921; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 4)
      London; begins "Dear Sir, Mr. Bernard Shaw is at present staying in Wales"
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter Signed: to George Herbert Thring, Jan. 18, 1924; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 5)
      London; begins "Dear Sir, Mr. Bernard Shaw desires me to say that the"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, Sept. 11, 1925; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 6)
      London; Miss Patch was having foot trouble; begins "Dear Mr. Shaw, Your letter has just arrived. It is the right big toe"
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter: to Miss Summer Boyd, Dec. 18, 1925; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 7)
      London; with pencil note added at bottom by a third person; begins "Dear Madam / Mr. Bernard Shaw desires me to say"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to St. John Ervine [initialed] plus Typed Letter from G.B.S. to Ervine, Nov. 14, 1929; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 8)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Ervine, I was so taken aback by your attack on me yesterday"
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter Signed: to J.W. Robertson Scott, Sept. 7, 1936; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 9)
      London; begins "Dear Sir, Mr. Bernard Shaw asks me to say that he has"
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter Signed: to J.W. Robertson Scott, Sept. 29, 1936; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 10)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Robertson Scott / Mr. Shaw keeps all his"
    - Patch, Blanche Eliza: Typed Letter Signed: to J.W. Robertson Scott, Oct. 6, 1936; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 11)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Robertson Scott / Mr. Shaw is not very helpful."
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to James Habgood, Feb. 7, 1942; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 12)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; a Shaw-by-proxy letter; concerns a request for a copy of The Irrational Knot; begins "Dear Sir, Mr. Bernard Shaw asks me to say that as he only"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to Alan Dent, May 5, 1942; 1 leaf + 2 (Box 29, Folder 13)
      London; this is a letter-by-proxy of Bernard Shaw; the old friend referred to in the body of the letter is Max Beerbohm; included is a note from Alan Dent to Dan Laurence
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to J.W. Robertson Scott, Feb. 3, 1944; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 14)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Robertson Scott, I have been living in London since"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to Mr. Clench, Aug. 13, 1945; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 29, Folder 15)
      London; includes note by Bernard F. Burgunder on separate leaf; the "German" referred to in the body of the letter is F.E. Loewenstein; begins "Dear Mr. Clench, Many thanks for the information about the Annuity."
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Nov. 1945; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 16)
      Begins "While I know it is your love of teasing that made you write the"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Nov. 26, 1945; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 17)
      London; begins "Dear, long-suffering GBS, As a start I will say that I'm glad I ended my previous letter"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to Robert F. Rattray, Apr. 28, 1949; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 29, Folder 18)
      London; with explanatory note added on separate leaf by Bernard F. Burgunder; begins "Dear Robert, All right. I'll be with you next Thursday"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Note: to George Bernard Shaw, ca. June 9, 1949; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 19)
      With a holograph answer by Shaw dated June 9, 1949
    - Patch, Blanche: Autograph Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin [?], May 17, 1954; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 20)
      London; begins "I have solved this / mystery by going to the"
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed: to Mr. Sandford, Feb. 5, 1956; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 21)
      London; concerning the survival of Bernard shaw's private diaries; begins "Dear Mr. Sandford, Many thanks for returning the note book."
    - Patch, Blanche: Typed Letter Signed & Autograph Letter Signed: to Bernard F. Burgunder, Jan. 7, 1960 - Oct. 23, 1963; 9 leaves + envelopes + 7 (Box 29, Folder 22)
      7 letters; with carbon copies of four letters, Dec. 15, 1959 - Oct. 9, 1963, to Blanche Patch from Bernard F. Burgunder
    - Patch, Blanche: Letters from unidentified correspondents, 1945-1962; 4 leaves + envelope (Box 29, Folder 23)
      3 items; includes a rather gossipy letter from "William," on R&R Clark stationery; they were Shaw's printers
    - Patch, Edith: Autograph Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin, Dec. 7, 1966; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 24)
      St. Leonards-on-Sea; begins "Dear Mr. Mushlin / This is Edith Patch"
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Typed Manuscript: portions of manuscript of Pearson's biography of GBS, n.d.; 13 leaves + 1 (Box 29, Folder 25)
      On the original typescript are holograph corrections by Shaw; included is a note by Bernard Burgunder, dated May 21, 1970
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Typed Manuscript: Bernard Shaw, His Life and Personality[fragment], 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 26)
      Including long handwritten addition by Shaw concerning Getting Married and Misalliance; identified by a pencil note signed "H.P." partly on verson of unidentified printed proof with some pencil corrections; published on pp. 284-5 of Pearson's book
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Typed Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin, Mar. 4, 1951; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 27)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Mushlin, Miss Patch tells me that you are"
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Autograph Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin, Mar. 6, 1951; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 28)
      London; begins "If you could come / tomorrow (Wednesday)"
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Autograph Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin, Mar. 22, 1951; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 29)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Mushlin / Thank you so much for / your"
    - Pearson, Hesketh: Autograph Letter Signed: to M. Harry Mushlin, Mar. 27, 1951; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 30)
      London; begins "Dear Mr. Mushlin / Thanks for letting me know"
    - Pember, Frank: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, June 10, 1931; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 31)
      London; some confusion as to who signed a letter from Shaw to Mr. Pember, Shaw or Blanche Patch; begins "Dear Sir / We shall be so very"
    - Pember, Frank: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, July 8, 1931; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 32)
      London; Mr. Pember seems to think that "Blanche Patch" is Shaw's pseudonym rather than his secretary; begins "Dear Sir / I hope you will not mind if I have used"
    - Percy, (Saville) Esmé: Typed Manuscript: Bernard Shaw: Personal Memories, May 11, 1955; 5 leaves (Box 29, Folder 33)
      London? Transcription from a telediphone [sic] recording; Percy was an actor who did some of Shaw's plays; the program was given to the B.B.C.
    - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William, baron: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Aug 11, 1938; carbon copy; 1 leaf + 2 (Box 29, Folder 34)
      Concerning publication of a Gujarati translation of St. Joan; with Typed Letter [carbon] to R.J. Udani from Pethick-Lawrence, Aug. 11, 1932; and Typed Letter Signed to Pethick-Lawrence from A.C. Brown, Aug. 3, 1932
    - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William, baron: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Oct. 3, 1922; carbon copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 35)
      Concerns performances of Eurhythmy; begins "Dear Mr. Bernard Shaw, Thank you very much for your"
    - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William, baron: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, May 11, 1938; carbon copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 36)
      Recommending Karel Capek's play Power and Glory; begins "Dear Mr. Bernard Shaw, I do not know whether you have seen"
    - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William, baron: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, May 16, 1938; carbon copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 37)
      Begins "Dear Mr. Bernard Shaw, Thank you very much for your"
    - Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick William, baron: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Oct. 22, 1946; carbon copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 38)
      Thanking Shaw for his letter to The Times published Oct. 21; begins "Dear Mr. Bernard Shaw, May I as a quite unimportant member"
    - Pettinati, Nino: Typed Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch, Dec. 9, 1952; 3 leaves (Box 29, Folder 39)
      Turin; concerns the publishing history of Shaw's works in Italy, as well as the Italian version of Miss Patch's Thirty Years...; Mr. Pettinati translated some Shaw into Italian; begins "Very dear Miss Blanche, Please, excuse my "Blanche," but how could an unrepentant shavian [sic] as I am"
    - Pilecki, Gerard Anthony: Typed Letter Signed: to Bernard F. Burgunder, Dec. 3 & 11, 1958; 6 leaves (Box 29, Folder 40)
      2 letters; on the bibliography of Shaw's Geneva
    - Pitman, Sir (Isaac) James: Materials relating to the Proposed British Alphabet, n.d.; copy; 14 items (Box 29, Folder 41)
      Included: Epitome of affidavit... (on validity of Shaw's Will) February 8, 1956; Epitome intended to be helpful to lobby correspondents (on Shaw's Will) March 23, 1956; George Bernard Shaw: some facts, February 20, 1957; Bath Chronicle article, March 22, 1957; A specimen of the new British alphabet, April 1957; Notes for press conference, December, 1957; Advertisement regarding George Bernard Shaw, deceased December 1957; Toronto Star article, January 1958; Explanatory memorandum containing Lists of Sounds, February 1958; A phonetic alphabet, Print in Britain, August 1960; Extract from the Will (Shaw's); Shaw notecard on phonetic spelling (with holograph note), January 27, 1942; Shaw's Orthography of the Bomb, December 27, 1945; My fair ladies and gentlemen, November 1958
    - Plunkett, Sir Horace Curzon: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Nov. 15, 1915; carbon copy; 2 leaves (Box 29, Folder 42)
      Concerns objections to production of O'Flaherty, V.C. in Dublin; the original of this letter has not been located; begins "My dear Shaw, I hear you are in direct communication"
    - Pritzker, Lee: Typed Manuscript: The Saint of Ayot St. Lawrence, Oct. 1950; mimeo; 1 item (Box 29, Folder 43)
      Article on pp. 3-4; the author was founder of the first Shaw Society of Canada; begins "Canadian Vegetarian Union News Bulletin
    - Rank, Joseph Arthur: Typed Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, Oct. 27, 1943; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 44)
      Surrey; discussion of the making of a film version of Caesar and Cleopatra; date of Shaw's answer given, in Shaw's hand; begins "Dear Mr. Bernard Shaw / I entirely agree that the artistic"
    - Reyding, A.: Typed Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, Mar. 21, 1920; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 45)
      Amsterdam; Mr. Reyding represented the Society of Authors in the Netherlands; the letter concerns translations into Flemish, and whether they copyright those into Dutch; begins "Dear Sir, In answer to yours of the 16th inst. I beg to observe the"
    - Rhondda, Margaret Haig Thomas, 2nd viscountess: Typed Manuscript: Untitled, ca. 1950; 14 leaves (Box 29, Folder 46)
      Includes holograph sheets of notes; concerns George Bernard Shaw
    - Rhondda, Margaret Haig Thomas, 2nd viscountess: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 47)
      London; concerns serializing the letters of Ellen Terry; begins "My dear Mr. Shaw / Is there any chance of getting the Serial"
    - Rhondda, Margaret Haig Thomas, 2nd viscountess: Typed Letter: to George Bernard Shaw, Jan. 19, 1923; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 48)
      Request for an article on child abuse; begins "Dear Mr. Shaw, I have read the letter you wrote to"
    - Rhondda, Margaret Haig Thomas, 2nd viscountess: Telegram to George Bernard Shaw, May 23, 1945; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 49)
      London; begins "Have written to The Times on receipt of your wire"
    - Rhondda, Margaret Haig Thomas, 2nd viscountess: Typed Letter: to Stephen Winsten, Jan. 1, 1946; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 50)
      Begins "Dear Sir, In Lady Rhondda's absense I am writing to acknowledge"
    - Richards, Ruth and Ulrich, Elizabeth: Typed Letter: Concerning the progress of Mr. Burgunder's reference question with regard to Agnes Claudius, former companion to Mrs. Patrick Campbell, Jan. 1968; copy; 5 leaves (Box 29, Folder 51)
      Wilkes-Barre, and University Park, Pennsylvania; some of the copies are signed
    - Roberts, Cecil: Typed Letter: to Gene Tunney, June 28, 1963; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 52)
      London; adecdote about Shaw and Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "Dear Gene Tunney, I have been staying with my friend Dr. A.L. Rowse,"
    - Robinson, Lennox: Typed Letter Signed: to Alan Wade, Dec. 8, 1953; 2 leaves + 1 (Box 29, Folder 53)
      Dublin; concerns the history of the Irish Academy of Letters; Shaw was a Founding Member; begins "Dear Alan Wade / P.S. O'Hegarty tells me that some time ago you wrote to him"
    - Rodgers, Mrs. E.B.: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, Oct. 16, 1950; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 29, Folder 54)
      Oamaru, N. Zealand; fan letter; begins "Dear Mr. Shaw. I am taking the liberty of"
    - Royal Academy of Dramatic Art: Typed Letter Signed: bearing many signatures of various members, among them Shaw's [fragment], ca. 1927-28; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 29, Folder 55)
      London; appeal for funds to found a national theatre
    - Royal Society of Literature, Academic Committee: Typed Manuscript: Letters and related documents, 1911-1928; copy; 8 leaves + 1 (Box 29, Folder 56)
      Mimeographed, spirit-duplicated, and printed material from teh files of G.B. Shaw, who was a member of the Academic Committee; one item gives the rules of the Committee at the time of tis creation in 1911; others are concerned with producing a phonetic alphabet; includes note on separate leaf by Bernard F. Burgunder
    - Russell, Henry T. ("Tosti"): Typed Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch, Nov. 5, 1937; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 57)
      London; begins "My dear B.P. / I am off tomorrow to New York with the Duke of Windsor
    - Sadleir, Michael: Typed Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch, Aug. 3, 1955; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 58)
      London; concerns Miss Patch's dispute with Shaw's biographer, St. John Ervine, as to his use of Shaw's diaries; See: Patch, Blanche Typed Manuscript The Diaries...; Mr. Sadleir was manager at Constable's, Shaw's publishers; begins "Dear Miss Patch, There is little I can say by way of"
    - Salt, Henry Stephens: Autograph Letter Signed: to George Bernard Shaw, Sept. 18, 1928; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 59)
      Brighton; removed from the copy of Salt's book Memories of Bygone Eton(London: Hutchinson, 1928?) kept in the Burgunder Shaw Collection; begins "My dear Shaw, Remembering your affection / for"
    - Samuels, H.: Autograph Letter Signed: to Secretary of Hammersmith Socialist League, Emery Walker, ca. 1885-1886; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 29, Folder 60)
      Chelsea; with note on separate leaf by Bernard F. Burgunder; begins "Dear Comrade, As there is a probabillity [sic] of"
    - Saunders, H.M.: Autograph Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch, Oct. 17, 1951; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 61)
      Belfast; concerns a children's song, "Mother Tabbyskins"; begins "Dear Miss Patch. I remember my"
    - Saville, Agnes: Typed Letter: to Blanche Patch, Sept. 17, 1954; copy; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 62)
      London; Miss Patch was Shaw's secretary; on the same sheet is another copy of Cyril Maude's letter of November 18, 1950, to Miss Patch; begins "Dear Miss Patch, I was so very sorry to have had to leave immediately"
    - Scudamore, T.V.: Typed Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch, Apr. 17, 1951; 1 leaf (Box 29, Folder 63)
      Parkstone, Dorset; Shavian anecdotes; begins "Dear Madam:- I am thoroughly enjoying your book and would like to"
    - Shah, Hiralal Amritlal: Typed Manuscript Signed: The Late Mr. Bernard Shaw - When He Was In Bombay, July 1955; Carbon copy; 12 leaves (Box 29, Folder 64)
      English translation by the author of an article in Gujarati published in Prabuddha Jain, Bombay, Nov. 15, 1950, and reprinted in 1955; the article concerns Shaw's visit to Bombay in January 1933
    - Sharpe, A. Menzies: Typed Letter Signed: to Stanley Clench, May 30, 1939; 2 leaves (Box 29, Folder 65)
      Hertford; concerning some comments by Shaw on endocrinology; begins "Dear Mr. Clench, Thanks for yours of 26th inst. which came"
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to ?, postcard; 1 item (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "I was so touched by the very"
  - Shaw - Sz
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Notes Initialed: to [Ann Elder], 6 leaves (Box 30, Folder 1.5)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; 4 notes + 1 address + 1 list. Forms part of the Ann Elder Jackson Collection.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed; to Margaret Haig (Thomas) Rhondda, Viscountess, card; 1 item (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "Dear Rhonndda [sic] / We must & will meet"
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Letter Signed: to Sean O'Casey, Dec.; 1 leaf (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Christmas Card; no year is given
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Typed Letter: Business correspondence, Dec. 16, 1905 - Oct. 24, 1940; copy; 41 leaves + 1 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      34 letters; typed copies made for Shaw of letters by Charlotte Shaw and others concerning edition she helped prepare of Selected Passages from the Works of Bernard Shaw and Three Plays by Brieux; cross-reference cards have been made for the individual letters, by author, and for the books discussed
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to Brentano's, after Oct. 11, 1912; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 30, Folder 5)
      London; both the note and the envelope were found with letters received from George Bernard Shaw by Brentano's; the envelope is presumably to be dated ca. 1916
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Postcard Initialed: to Ann Elder, Feb.2, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 30, Folder 5.3)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "Why didn't you send down those proofs." Forms part of the Ann Elder Jackson Collection.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letters & Notes Signed & Initialed: to Ann Elder, Apr.29-Dec.28, 1914; 9 leaves (Box 30, Folder 5.4)
      [Various places] 4 letters and 5 postcards from 1914.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letters & Postcards Initialed: to Ann Elder, [1915]-Sept.15, 1915; 8 leaves (Box 30, Folder 5.5)
      [Various places; Torquay] 6 letters and 2 postcards from 1915
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letters & Postcard Initialed: to Ann Elder, Jan.1-Oct.1, 1916; 8 leaves (Box 30, Folder 5.6)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; 3 letters and 5 postcards from 1916. Forms part of the Ann Elder Jackson Collection.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to Ann Elder [initialed], Feb. 28, 1916; 1 leaf + 3 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with her Autograph Document "Extract from the Baptismal Register" certified copy, July 11, 1932; and a 4x5 photograph of her (ca. 1920?) taken and developed by George Bernard Shaw; and a printed Memorial Program dated April 5, 1929, for her sister Mary Stewart (Payne-Townshend) Cholmondeley; an explanatory note by Dan H. Laurence has been typed on a separate leaf; gift of Bernard F. Burgunder, Dec. 19, 1978
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to Arthur Brentano, Mar. 26, 1916; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "Dear Mr. Brentano / Thank you for your letter just"
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letters & Postcards Initialed: to Ann Elder, Jan.6-Nov.25, 1917; 6 leaves (Box 30, Folder 7.4)
      [Various places] 2 letters & 4 postcards from 1917. Forms part of the Ann Elder Jackson Collection.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letters & Postcards Initialed: to Ann Elder, Aug.25, 1919-Sept.24, 1928; 6 leaves (Box 30, Folder 7.5)
      [Various places] 3 letters & 2 postcards from 1919 to April 20,1920; 1 letter from Sept. 24, 1928. Forms part of the Ann Elder Jackson Collection.
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to Brentano's, Nov. 18, 1920; 1 leaf (Box 30, Folder 8)
      London; begins "Dear Sirs / I enclose a receipt for the cheque"
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Typed Letter: to Thomas Edward Lawrence, May 17, 1927; copy; 3 leaves (Box 30, Folder 9)
      Copies by Blanche Patch; See: Dunbar, Janet. Mrs. G.B.S., pp. 280-283, for background information; begins "I'd like to tell you something about myself."
    - Shaw, Charlotte (Payne-Townshend): Autograph Letter Signed: to Blanche Patch [initialed], June 3, 1928?; postcard; 1 item (Box 30, Folder 10)
      Sandwich; begins "Thank you for your letter."